The Bruce Simonds Papers
Yale University Music Library
The Bruce Simonds Papers
1910-1974
Misc. Ms. 308
Yale University Music Library
3
(4 boxes)
Music and other papers by and about the American pianist, composer, and educator Bruce Simonds (1895-1989)
Simonds, Bruce
Gerschefski, Edwin, 1909-1992
Simonds, Rosalind Brown
Conditions Governing Access
The Papers are open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Bruce Simonds Papers were bequeathed to the Music Library of Yale University in 1989.
Arrangement
In 4 series as follows: I. Music. II. Programs. III. Scrapbooks. IV. Miscellaneous.
Scope and Contents
The Bruce Simonds Papers document the careers of the pianist, composer, and educator Bruce Simonds and his wife, Rosalind Brown Simonds. Included are manuscript compositions by both composers, including songs, choral music, piano works, cadenzas for Mozart piano concertos, and early compositions with corrections, probably in the hand of Vincent d'Indy. In addition, the Papers hold photocopies of musical compositions by Edwin Gerschefski, programs, scrapbooks, and notes regarding performances given by Simonds' students.
Biographical / Historical
The pianist and composer Bruce Simonds was born in Bridgeport, Connecticut on July 5, 1895. Simonds spent nearly his entire adult life at Yale University, although he performed widely. He received his bachelor's degree from Yale in 1917. After further studies in London and Paris, Simonds joined the faculty of the Yale School of Music in 1921, where he taught for the next 52 years. From 1941 to 1954 he was Dean of the School of Music. Bruce Simonds died in Hamden, Connecticut on June 2, 1989.
Concertos (Piano) -- Scores; Organ music; Pianists -- United States; Piano music; Songs; Indy, Vincent d', 1851-1931; Simonds, Bruce; Simonds, Rosalind Brown
- Music, Series I
  - Music by Bruce Simonds, I.A
    - Inventory (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Choral works, I.A.1
      - Deep-sea soundings, 1 score (15 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 2)
        General
        Holograph in ink.
        SSAATTBB
        On title page: Deep-sea soundings. Words by Sarah Williams. Music by "Ayrault". Submitted for the Mendelssohn Club Prize competition. "With inconsiderable success" added in pencil.
        With 1 p. of text; 22 cm.
      - [Angelus enim domini] Motet, 1 score (3 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Holograph signed, in ink with annotations in French in pencil (d'Indy?), and corrections in blue pencil.
        SATB
        In Latin.
    - Songs, I.A.2
      - All night I ride, 1 score (4 p.); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Holograph signed, in ink.
        Words by P. Underwood.
        Dated: July 1922
      - Arabia, 1 score (6 p.); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Dated: "New Hampshire, July 1924"
      - Arabia, 1 score (6 p.); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Another photostat copy with list of piano music on back.
      - Berceuse, 1 score (3 p.); 36 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Holograph in ink, with corrections in pencil.
        Dated: September 1918
      - Bride song from "The prince's progress", 1 score (4 p.); 22 x 28 cm. (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Holograph signed, in pencil.
        Words by Christina G. Rosetti.
        Dated: July 6, 1912
      - The call, 1 score (3 p.); 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Holograph in ink with corrections in pencil and blue ink.
        Words by George Herbert.
        Dated: "BS 9/1/73"
      - Desire, 1 score (3 p.); 36 cm. (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Dated: 1954
      - Echo, 1 score (3 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 10)
        Words by C. Rossetti.
      - Exile, 1 score (2 p.); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
        Words by Walter de la Mare.
        Dated: "Jefferson Highlands-July 7 1924"
      - Exile, 1 score (2 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
        Dated: 1924
      - [Monodies] Cours I. Deux Monodies, 2 p. of music; 36 cm. (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Holograph signed, in ink with annotations in pencil in French (d'Indy?), and corrections in blue pencil.
        For voice alone.
        Contents: Monodie sans paroles; Monodie avec paroles.
        Monodie sans paroles lacks words; Monodie avec paroles has Latin text.
      - Moon-spell, 1 score (4 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 13)
        Words by B. Prescott Clark, jr.
        Dated: Sept. 1918
      - Nameless pain, 1 score (3 p.); 25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 14)
        Words by J. B. Aldrich.
        Dated: Sept. 7 1910
      - Peace, 1 score (3 p.); 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 15)
        Words by Henry Vaughan.
      - Silver, 1 score (4 p.); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 16)
        Holograph in ink (initialed "BS")
        Words by Walted de la Mare.
      - Spring pastoral, 1 score (3 p.); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 17)
        Holograph in ink with corrections in blue ink.
        Words by Elinor Wylie.
        Dated: Sept. 1974
      - [unidentified song], 1 p. of music; 24 cm. (Box 1, Folder 18)
        Fragment of piece.
    - Keyboard works, I.A.3
      - Barcarolle in A flat minor, 9 p. of music; 25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 19)
        For piano.
      - Bobolinks, 5 p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 20)
        Dated: "Jefferson Highlands, July 1924"
      - Butterflies, 4 p. of music; 25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 21)
        Dated: September 1, 1909
      - [Cadenzas, Mozart piano concerto, K. 246] Cadenzas for Mozart's concerto in C, K. 246, 3 p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 22)
        Holograph in ink, initialed "BS"
        Contents: cadenza for the first movement, cadenza for the second movement.
      - [Cadenza, Mozart piano concerto, K. 365] Cadenza for the first movement of Mozart's concerto in E-flat, K. 365, 4 p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 22a)
        For two pianos.
        Two copies.
        (Added August 1998)
      - [Cadenza, Mozart piano concerto, K. 365] Cadenza for the third movement of Mozart's concerto in E-flat, K. 365, 5 p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 22a)
      - [Cadenza, Mozart piano concerto, K. 466] Cadenza for the first movement of Mozart's concerto in D minor, K. 466, 3 p. of music; 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - [Cadenza, Mozart piano concerto K. 466] Cadenza for the third movement of Mozart's concerto in D minor, K. 466, 2 p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - [Cadenza, Mozart piano concerto K. 467] Cadenza for the first movement of Mozart's concerto in C, K. 467, 2 p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - [Cadenza, Mozart piano concerto K. 467] Cadenza for the third movement of Mozart's concerto in C, K. 467, 2 p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - [Cadenza, Mozart piano concerto K. 482] Cadenza for the first movement of Mozart's concerto in C, K. 482, 2 p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 25)
        Dated: 1971
      - [Cadenza, Mozart piano concerto K. 482] Cadenza for the third movement of Mozart's concerto in C, K. 482, 2 p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - [Cadenza, Mozart piano concerto K. 491] Cadenza to the first movement of Mozart's concerto in C minor, 3 p. of music; 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - [Cadenza, Mozart piano concerto K. 503] Cadenza for the first movement of Mozart's concerto in C, K. 503, 2 p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - [Cadenza, Mozart piano concerto K. 537] Cadenza for the first movement of Mozart's concerto in C, K. 537, 2 p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - [Cadenza, Mozart piano concerto] (Sketch for a cadenza to a piano concerto?), 1 p. of music; 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 29)
        Holograph in pencil (no signature or initials).
      - Choral Varié, 4 p. of music; 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 30)
        For organ.
      - Cloisters [rest of title unintelligible], 1 p. of music; 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 31)
        Holograph signed, in ink with corrections in lighter ink.
        Dated: July 1920
        Incomplete, lacks all after p. 1.
      - [Concerto, piano and orchestra, B-flat major] Concerto, 1 score (70 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 32)
        Holograph signed, in pencil with corrections in blue pencil.
        For piano and orchestra (full score).
      - [Concerto, piano and orchestra, B-flat major] Concerto in B-flat Major, 1 score (72 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 33)
        Dated: June 1918
        On title page: Concerto in B-flat Major (piano and orchestra). Bruce Simonds, 1918
      - [Concerto, piano and orchestra, B-flat major, arr.] Concerto in B-flat Major, 1 score (33 p.); 36 cm. (Box 1, Folder 34)
        Holograph in ink with corrections in pencil and blue pencil.
        Accompaniment for second piano.
      - [Concerto, piano and orchestra, B-flat major, arr.] Concerto in B flat major, 1 score (33 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Clytie, 4 p. of music; 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 35)
        Dated: "1918?-"
      - Friday sheet, 4 p. of music; 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 36)
        Holograph signed, in ink with markings in pencil.
      - [Fugues, organ] Cours II Sect. I. Fugue, 6 p. of music; 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Gigue, 3 p. of music; 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 38)
        Holograph signed, in ink with annotations in French in pencil (d'Indy?).
      - [Preludes, piano] Prelude, 4 p. of music; 21 x 27 cm. (Box 1, Folder 39)
      - [Preludes, piano] Prelude, 2 p. of music; 21 x 27 cm. (Box 1, Folder 40)
      - [Preludes on Gregorian themes. Dies irae] Dorian prelude on "Dies irae" for organ, 13 p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 41)
        Dated: "New Haven-Jefferson Highlands June-Aug. 1924"
      - [Preludes on Gregorian themes. Dies irae] Dorian prelude on "Dies irae" for organ, 14 p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 41)
        Holograph signed, in ink with corrections in red ink and pencil.
      - [Preludes on Gregorian themes. Dies irae] Dorian prelude on "Dies irae" for organ, 14 p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 41)
        Another ink copy in Yale Music Library Misc. Ms. 146.
      - [Preludes on Gregorian themes. Iam sol recadit] Prelude on "Iam sol recadit igneus" (eighth mode), 7 p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 42)
        Holograph signed, in ink with corrections in pencil.
        Dated: "Jefferson Highlands-Aug.-Sept. 1924"
      - [Preludes on Gregorian themes. Iam sol recadit] [Two preludes on Gregorian themes for organ.] Prelude on "Iam sol recadit" (eigth mode), 9 p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 42)
        Holograph signed, in ink with corrections in red ink, blue pencil, and pencil.
        Caption title.
        On title page: "Two preludes on Gregorian themes for organ"
        Dated: "Jefferson Highlands, Aug.-Sept. 1924"
      - [Preludes on Gregorian themes. Iam sol recadit] [Two preludes on Gregorian themes for organ.] Prelude on "Iam sol recadit" (eigth mode), 9 p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 42)
        Another ink copy in Yale Music Library Misc. Ms. 146
      - Scotch cap: English country dance tune, 3 leaves of music; 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 43)
        Holograph in pencil.
        For 2 pianos.
      - Scotch cap: English country dance tune, 1 score (11 p.); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 43)
        Dated: "Randolph-Sept. 1930, revised-New Haven Oct. 1931"
      - Scotch cap: English country dance tune, 1 score (12 p.); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 43)
        Dated: Oct. 1931
      - Scotch cap: English country dance tune, 1 score (10 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 43)
      - Scotch cap: English country dance tune, 1 score (11 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 43)
      - "Sweet Kate": English country dance tune, 1 score (16 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 44)
        Holograph signed, in pencil, with corrections in ink.
        Dated: "Cummington-Randolph, August 1930"
      - "Sweet Kate": English country dance tune, 1 score (15 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 44)
      - "Sweet Kate": English country dance tune, 1 score (18 p.); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 44)
      - "Sweet Kate": English country dance tune, 1 score (18 p.); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 44)
        Holograph signed, in blue and black ink.
      - Theme and variations in C sharp minor for pianoforte, 9 p. of music; 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 45)
        Formerly Yale Music Library Misc. Ms. 188
      - There, 2 p. of music; 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 46)
        Holograph signed, in ink with corrections and date in pencil.
        Dated: May 1921
      - [unidentified work] (title unintelligible), 5 p. of music; 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - [unidentified work], 3 p. of music; 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - [unidentified work], 3 p. of music; 34 cm (Box 1, Folder 49)
        Dated: "Paris, 1919"
    - Instrumental solo with accompaniment, I.A.4
      - Habanera, 12 p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 50)
        Holograph, in pencil.
        For violin solo and piano.
      - Habanera, 1 score (12 p.) + 1 part (6 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 50)
        For violin and piano.
        Dated: "Randolph, September 1929"
      - Habanera, 1 score (15 p.) + and 1 part (7 p.); 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 50)
        New York: Carl Fischer, Inc. [c. 1933]
        Pl. no. 26284-20
        Publisher's no. Ox. 1306
      - Madrigal pour deux violons et piano, 1 score (6 p.) + 1 part (2 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 51)
        Holograph signed, in ink with corrections in red pencil and pencil.
        For 2 violins and piano.
        Dated: June 26, 1919
        Incomplete, lacks second violin part.
      - [Sonatas, violin, violoncello and piano] Sonate pour violon, violoncelle et piano. 1er mouvement, 1 score (16 p.) + 2 parts (5 p., 7 p.); 36 cm. (Box 1, Folder 52)
        For violin, cello and piano.
      - [Sonatas, violin, violoncello and piano] Sonate pour violon, violoncelle et piano. 2e mouvement, 14 p. of music + 1 part (5 p.); 36 cm. (Box 1, Folder 52)
        Holograph signed, in ink with annotations in French in pencil (d'Indy?) and corrections in red pencil.
        Incomplete, lacks violoncello part.
      - [unidentified work], 1 score (28 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 53)
        Holograph, in ink with corrections in pencil.
        Incomplete, lacking movement I and all but p. 1 of movement IV.
        For piano and unidentified solo instrument.
    - Miscellaneous, I.A.5
      - [unidentified work], 1 p. of music; 16 x 24 cm. (Box 1, Folder 54)
        Holograph in ink, with annotations in French in pencil (d'Indy?), and corrections in blue pencil.
        For unidentified solo instrument.
  - Music by Rosalind Brown Simonds, I.B
    - Songs, I.B.1
      - La Dernière Feuille, 4 p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Folder 55)
        Words by Gauthier.
        Dated: June 22 1917
      - Mélodie, 4 p. of music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 56)
        Words by Victor Kinon.
        Dated: May 1918
    - Keyboard works, I.B.2
      - [Concerto, piano and orchestra, E minor] Pianoforte concerto in E minor, 1 score (39 p.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 57)
        Holograph (signed in ink) in pencil with corrections in ink.
      - [Fugues, organ] Fugue a 4 voix, 4 p. of music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 58)
        Dated: Avril 1918
      - [Fugues, piano] Fugue in G minor for pianoforte, 4 p. of music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 59)
        Dated: 1913
      - [Fugues, piano] Fugue pour piano, 3 p. of music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 60)
        Holograph signed, in ink with annotations in French in ink (d'Indy?).
      - Menuet, 3 p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Folder 61)
        On title page: "Examen du IIme cours-Ier section"
      - Nocturne en sol, 3 p. of music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 62)
        Dated: Jan. 1917
      - Prélude, 3 p. of music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 63)
        Dated: January 1918
      - The water midden, 4 p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Orchestra works, I.B.3
      - Esquisses (sketch), 3 p. of music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 65)
        Piano score, with indications for instrumental scoring written in.
      - [Overture, G minor] Overture in G minor (sketch), 2 p. of music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 66)
        Piano score with indications for instrumental scoring written in.
      - [Overture, G minor] Overture In G minor (sketch), 10 p. of music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 66)
        Holograph signed, in ink with corrections in ink and pencil.
        Dated: 1915
        On title page: "Sketch of overture in G minor"
      - Petit poème pour orchestre, 10 p. of music; 36 cm. (Box 2, Folder 67)
        Piano score.
        Dated: "July-August 1917"
  - Music by others, I.C
    - Solitude, Bozyan, H. Frank (Hagop Frank), 1899-1965; 4 p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 2, Folder 68)
      Dated: "August 1924. Newport, R.I."
    - Four preludes (nos. 1, 2, 3, and 6 from Six preludes for piano), Gerschefski, Edwin, 1909-1992; 12 p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Folder 69)
      Holograph signed in ink.
    - Gebrauch Musik, Gerschefski, Edwin, 1909-1992; 8 p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Folder 69)
      Photocopy of manuscript, signed in ink.
      Dated: movements I-III, V, "May 8, 1934, New York City"; movement IV, "May 3, 1934, New York City"; movement VI, "August 6, 1934, N.Y. City"; movement VII and VIII, "Oct 10, 1934, NY City"
    - Portrait of an artist and other short piano pieces, Gerschefski, Edwin, 1909-1992; 9 p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Folder 69)
      Dated: (not all movements dated) Lament, "Oct. 1934, New York City"; Mimi's lullaby, "Dec. 16, 1934, New York City"; Allegretto, Jan, 8, 1936, N.Y.C."
    - Six waltzes, Gerschefski, Edwin, 1909-1992; 4 p. of music; 39 cm. (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Suite for the left hand, Gerschefski, Edwin, 1909-1992; 11 p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Two dances, Gerschefski, Edwin, 1909-1992; 11 p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Sonata for piano, Jones, Collier, 1928-2013; 14 p. of music; 32 cm. (Box 2, Folder 70)
      Photocopy of manuscript, bound.
      Inscribed on title page: "Best regards from Charlie"
    - Sonatina for piano, Joséph, Bruce; 9 p. of music; 31 cm. (Box 2, Folder 71)
      Photocopy of ms.
      Dated: 1946
      Inscribed to Bruce Simonds on title page.
    - Sept pièces faciles à deux voix. -- Paris: B. Roudanez [c.1919], Reuger, Saga; 7 p. of music; 33 cm. (Box 2, Folder 72)
      Pl. no. B.R. 729
      Inscribed to Rosalind Brown [Simonds] on title page.
- Programs, Series II
  Annotations regarding performances appear on the verso of many programs.
  - Yale programs, 1932-1964 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Miscellaneous programs, 1930-1949 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Miscellaneous programs, 1950-1964 (Box 2, Folder 75)
- Scrapbooks, Series III
  Scope and Contents
  Scrapbooks contain programs and clippings from Bruce and Rosalind Simonds' performance and composition careers.
  Scrapbooks were copied onto acid-free paper and the originals discarded.
  - 1926-1937, 22 p. (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - 1930-1932, 67 p. (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - 1932-1934, 70 p. (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - 1937-1940, 74 p. (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - 1940-1944, 63 p. (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - 1944-1949, 92 p. (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - 1949-1954, 64 p. (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - 1954-1957, 44 p. (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - 1957-1961, 85 p. (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - 1961-1964, 66 p. (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - One scrapbook of Bruce Simond's students, 1948-1954; 120 p. (Box 4, Folder 87)
    His students' names are underlined in red pencil.
- Miscellaneous, Series IV
  - Notes regarding student performances, probably from a piano class (Box 4, Folder 86)
    Two notebooks: "Meeting, Feb. 23, 1933"; "Second meeting, March 23,1933"
  - Outlines of musical history: development of music through Beethoven, arranged by Bruce Simonds and Hugh Smith. -- [New Haven, Conn., Whitlock's Book Store, Inc.] c1932, 2 p l. 86 numb. l. 28 cm. (Box 4, Folder 88)
    At head of title: Yale University. School of Music.
    Annotated copy, inscribed "Bruce Simonds."
  - Norfolk Music School of Yale University, 1944-1959; 15 items (Box 4, Folder 89)
    Includes brochure, lists of piano compositions to be studied, rosters, and an article.